welcome everyone today I'm talking with
Daniel Craig about a book project that
we are working on together Daniel is a
former student of mine he's also done a
lot of work putting together a set of
conferences
having to do with the effects of
psychedelics on cognition and the way
they might perhaps afford zappy eventual
development and Daniel's had a
significant influence on my father
around those topics
when Daniel is also somebody who is
currently actually working with me on
the book were in the process of writing
it right now
the book is called the cognitive
continuum from insight to enlightenment
so let's jump right in to what exactly
we're going to be discussing the title
in particular is very significant
would you like to provide an elaboration
of why this book is called the cognitive
continuum right so the main idea about
that is the thesis that there's a
continuum between the kinds of cognitive
machinery that's at work in something
like insight problem-solving like when
we are having a farm moment and then
that machinery is taken up and extended
into something like what people call the
flow experience and we can talk about
each one of these in more detail as we
go along and then in turn that the
machinery the flow experience is
extended and exacted up into mystical
experiences and then that machinery is
in turn can sometimes have an impact on
people in which they seek to transform
the structure of their identity the
structure of their lives and that's a
transformative experience and then when
that in turn is making available a set
of practices and skills and virtues that
allows people to address the perennial
problems that beset human beings
problems of self-deception and
self-destructive behavior then we're
arguing at least that that's at least a
good operational definition of what it
is to have achieved enlightenment and so
in a sense right what you're seeing is
the same machinery being recursively
exact it and expanded and complexified
and so there's a continuum and what that
means is we can take some of the
mystique that has been typically
associated with things like
enlightenment or even with mystical
experiences or awakening experiences and
by putting it on a continuum with this
machinery that's more readily understood
and studied within cognitive psychology
and cognitive science we can bring a
deeper understanding which of course
affords both you know better science but
we also are going to emphasize in the
book how that deeper understanding
affords enhancing people's ability to
practice
you know well basically a course of the
cultivation of wisdom and enlightenment
that practical edge is I think one of
the things I'm looking forward to the
most in elaborating this framework and
we're gonna be providing some guidelines
on how to structure your own
enlightenment practice based on this
definition now regarding the
demystification I want to talk a little
bit about that because one of the
interesting things about the kinds of
experiences associated different
Lightman's if that's the experience of
divine union where you are your egos
sort of shattered into the infinite
expanse or the more visionary types of
experiences attains by angels demons etc
you know the Buddha during his
enlightenment process he's visited by
Mara who tells him with all of this
visionary material and there is a very
very it's almost very likely that at
many times during the process of
exploring these experiences that the
content is going to be conflated with
the reality of what's happening right
because there's this issue that you've
talked about with higher states of
consciousness that they're infused with
the sense of truth in the sense of
significance yeah so that's one of the
things that really interests me about
these these experiences it's a it's a
problem when I presented some work on it
and an issue I call on to normativity
what that means is let's say let's I
think it's non controversial to say that
mystical experiences are some kind of
altered state of consciousness I think
that's fairly non-controversial but
these experiences tend to have and
there's work supporting this by other
people Newburgh Gate and Taylor people
like that but anyways they when people
have these experiences they're very
different from how they normally relate
to their other altered states of
consciousness so for example if you're
dreaming when you wake up out of your
dream and notice how we use the
awakening metaphor when you wake up out
of your dream you say oh well the dream
wasn't real this is reality right now
what's really interesting is why that's
going on and it has to do I think very
very quickly with the fact that we have
this sort of overall pattern of
intelligibility that makes sense
and not just in an intellectual sense it
gives us kind of a good optimal grip on
the world and when when the dream state
we can't fit that in and any kind of
sort of coherent fashion to that and so
that's not real that makes sort of sense
to everybody's you know okay but what's
interesting is when people go into these
higher states of consciousness they do
something very different they come back
and say no no that was really real and
all of this this everyday experience is
somehow less real less illusory that's
and that's the Anto part being reality
the normativity that comes in onto
normativity is that they feel called to
transform themselves and their lives and
often quite radical manner so that they
can come into a greater existential
conformity to that that increased
realness they want to get back to it and
this sort of speaks to that there's this
drive for human beings to a drive for a
realization in both senses of the word
like the sense of insight and the sense
of coming into contact with which with
what is most real now because of that
font or normativity as you said people
come out of it and they feel called and
they feel called to what is most real
and what could happen is they can attach
that to any particular proposition or
content or pictorial content they might
use to try and make sense or interpret
that and so what can happen is that
sense of entre normativity can get
transferred into a kind of authority for
their particular claims and that that
can be very very very dangerous because
I think you can make a very good case
where as we do in the book that there's
a procedural or perspectival even a
participatory sense these are different
kinds of knowing that in which we can
make a good case that they're being
really optimized and enhanced in their
function so another way of saying it is
your cognition is being made to function
much much better and its abilities to
sort of get a grip on reality and to
cool and to work coordinate right the
conformity of your sense of idea
to how you're identifying with the world
and how you're identifying the world
that's all
procedurally being enhanced and that's
very different from whatever particular
metaphysical claims people make because
people can come out of these experiences
and they'll say oh now I know there's a
god or they can come out of these
experiences and they're equally ecstatic
and saying now I know there's no God and
so if you try and get any sort of
consent so this is not like a hug it's
not like a hugs knee and perennialism I
don't mean I don't think you're gonna
find sort of a set of core propositions
that everybody's going to agree on other
than propositions that are sort of
reflectively descriptive of the
phenomenology right but any attempts to
describe to sort of extrapolate that
because of the entre normativity into a
claim about the metaphysical structure
of reality that's very very questionable
so the distinction we make is a
distinction between giving up on the
idea that we're getting you know sort of
arcane metaphysical knowledge of reality
and instead thinking what's happening in
these states and what they're actually
calling to you is towards wisdom right
with that and enlightenment and and
you'll even see this in the traditions
where for example the Buddha you know
famously does not want to offer any
metaphysical speculations and true
metaphysical questions make metaphysical
claims about Nirvana the state of
enlightenment instead he wants to help
people cultivate the wisdom to realize
that statement right relationships at
the end of the day are the most
important yes enlightenment is an
existential mode right it's a way of
relating to self to world to other which
promotes an optimal sort of interaction
and within that definition of optimal we
also need to include a definition of
ethics and how Ethics manifests yes
there is no enlightenment without ethics
however there could be wisdom I think an
interesting distinction that I've
learned from looking into Jewish
philosophy is the difference between you
could call it microcosmic wisdom and
macrocosmic wisdom the wisdom with a
lowercase or a capital W but wisdom is
just a kind of expertise in Hebrew you
can use the word wisdom to refer to
Graham
who's really good at knitting she has
wisdom in let's get it huh yeah but um
there's something greater least when you
say Street was that can right be another
kind of expertise right but if you're if
you have to be Street buys you know that
might mean that for example you're
really gonna like physically defending
yourself you have to right right we're
just not necessarily something that we
really want people to have to be that
while it's still good skill but the one
of the fundamentally distinctive things
about enlightenment compared to just
wisdom per se is the ethical norm that
comes with it there is no action that is
unethical that is an enlightened action
I think it's a pretty good standard
asset for that mm-hmm
one framing that came up as you were
talking about the auto normativity of
the states and such is the difference
between expression and explanation so if
you look into ancient philosophy I have
a double major in cognitive science and
in philosophy specialized in ancient
philosophy they do a lot of good
thinking about things like prophetic
visionary states of consciousness which
I'm particularly fascinated in one thing
that comes up is that the transcendent
state the transcendent quality of
universe of the universe is just too
much for human beings to handle and this
is something that you emphasized I think
even in the first lecture of the intro
to cognitive science course we are
epidemic about there are very real
constraints on our cognition such that
certain things we actually can't know
directly yes
so our cognition has all these
interesting mechanisms these excitation
mechanisms to cross reference
information to bounce information around
different parts of the brain so for
example in the psychedelic state if
you're on under the influence of LSD
there is an increase in activation
between the part of your temporal lobe
which projects back into your occipital
lobe and this seems to increase the
likelihood of personally relevant mental
imagery coming into your experience so
your visual cortex in these states is
actually translating non visual
information into a visual metaphor yes
so that you can more readily grasp the
relationship underlying the image right
and this comes up in the philosophy of
my monami
he's flashed out what prophecy is and
how it works and I think it's a really
good framework here articulates the mind
is being cut up into a rational faculty
and an imaginative faculty when there
are things that the rational part of
your mind can't comprehend it overflows
into the imaginative part of your mind
and your imagination then has to do all
of these metaphorical abstract
networking things in order to make sense
of that which is too much for the
rational mind to understand so your mind
is in a very real way simply trying to
express things that it can't quite grasp
any other way right and if we look also
at Carl Jung's philosophy of dreams one
of the things that comes up and I know
Jordan Peterson has mentioned that ideas
will first show up to you in your dreams
in their sort of inchoate form and then
as they become more and more refined you
are may be able to articulate them more
but at first they might seem as though
they have a lot of weight a lot of
magnitude you might be perplexed even by
a dream even though it doesn't have this
aunt enormity thing going on there might
be something that sticks with you and
your dream and you're like hmm why is
that happening
and why do I feel so compelled to dig
deeper so these imaginative flourishes
that your mind is capable of performing
are ways of getting us to comprehend
relationships to self world other which
are fundamentally a little bit beyond
our scope of understanding and by
continually doing this we are
continually expanding our capacity to
know more to integrate more perspectives
to internalize more perspectives and to
better be able to relate to a broader
array of people if we apply this frame
which you know has some roots in ancient
philosophy of what exactly cognition is
doing when we are experiencing
imaginative interesting elaborative
dreamlike phenomena we can use that to
integrate that content much more readily
and to apply it to our lives the fact
that right we can use that imaginal
material in order to well as you said to
counteract pathological processes on one
hand and potentially afford
a kind of flourishing engagement with
oneself in the world that's exactly what
we mean by this content doesn't give you
knowledge but if dealt with in the right
way it can really afford the cultivation
of wisdom right it certainly gives you
some perspective yes there was something
I wanted to talk about regarding the
particularity of different languages
used to train the brain okay it's coming
back okay so one question that I've
gotten from a few people when I've been
discussing my progress in book is why
the term enlightenment mm-hm
and I think that's the whole idea of set
that we've been discussing here oh well
you know there's a whole set of
traditions which have this particular
kind of language which helps you to
train yourself in a particular kind of
way is actually you can have more ideal
relationships with self world at other
the term enlightenment is actually
really important because it's nested in
with this network of associations coming
from the spiritual heritage of
intellectual history and I think we
would be very remiss to forego that for
a more neutral term you know I returned
before I started looking into a lot of
the stuff that I've used which is
analogous is like cognitive optimization
for example that's a perfectly good
neutral term that you could use but it
doesn't really help us to yoke these
ideas to the traditions that have
provided us languages and practices that
we can utilize to actually cultivate the
state I agree and that and it's not only
the history that we don't want to lose
thread the thread of we're losing some
of the phenomenology listen to the word
insight we typically use perceptual
attentional metaphors to try and explain
significant cognitive changes in the
sight sight is being invoked
enlightenment has to do with it
transformation of your ability to look
and see because now things are lit in a
way that whether they were previously
dark to you now of course there's other
other metaphors Buddha means awake and
when the awakening is also a metaphor
because that's again if you think
when you wake up your this is a very
comprehensive transformation of your
entire existential mode and it's not
only sort of liberating you from the
illusions of the dream it's affording
you exploring and entering into a
relationship with the wire real world
and and so I think not only should we as
you said not only should we keep
continuity with this historical heritage
because we want to be able to connect
that literature it might not be as
theoretically valuable as we people
might think but as we've just said it's
sappy enchilada training valuable as
training value is undeniable and we also
want to keep I think the connection with
this language precisely because that
language the terms of cognitive
optimization I think should be paired
with things like enlightenment because
cognitive opponet optimization gives
priority to the functional aspect of
what we're talking about terms like
enlightenment gives priority to the
existential and the phenomenological
aspects of what we're talking about
right different languages for different
times for this yes yeah so one thing I
want to talk about a little bit but is
relevant because recently I watched one
of your conversations with Jonathan
Paige oh yes and there was a point where
you had mentioned oh I'm not taking an
eclectic approach to this and he kind of
laughed and said I don't know about that
John yes so I want to talk about the
differences between the kind of
autodidactic new-age eclecticism you
mentioned the perennialism of Huxley
it was kind of like the opposite yeah
those two poles I want to avoid both
yeah so let's unstrap a little bit about
that where are we fitting into those
bowls so I mean I for me and I think
this is also the case for you the model
that I take from this is the model from
cognitive science and so as opposed to a
collective system I argue that there's
sort of the the most powerful the most
prescriptive vision of cognitive science
is one of synoptic integration and so
what I'm trying to do as a cognitive
scientist is I'm trying to pick up on
the fact that we have all these
specialized disciplines that study
different acts aspects or levels of the
mind neuroscience that is the brain
artificial intelligence machine learning
star studies information processing
ecology studies behavior and mystic
studies language anthropology studies
culture and they each have their own
language and they each have their own
methods of gathering evidence and the
problem that you face with that is
that's wonderful and that's given us
this tremendous you know advance but
those different disciplines we are
correlated with particular levels of
reality like I said the brain level the
information processing the behavioral
and here's the thing it is highly likely
that those different levels the brain
level the information processing level
the behavioral level are not causally
distinct from each like they're
interacting with each other they're
constraining and affording each other in
very very powerful ways and so the
problem we have is we don't have
anything that's talking about the
relations between the levels because
each one of these disciplines is pitched
at a level so what do we need well we
need a discipline that does synoptic
integration it tries to of provide a
bridging vocabulary a kind of you know a
kind of cognitive vocabulary a
conceptual vocabulary and the kind of
theoretical grammar so that you can get
these different disciplines to
insightfully talk to each other mutually
inform and transform each other in an
insightful manner that's not the
integration it's not saying it's not
saying that all the disciplines are
saying the same thing it is not saying
that I can just pick and choose as I
wish from each one of these in some
eclectic fashion it's saying no no there
is a relationship there's a two-way
movement of understanding you can pull
back towards sort of an integrative
stance
what's the bridging language right
that's half of what you need because
that picks up on the interactions we
also need to go back down into the
particular disciplines for what their
particular knowledge about what each
level is doing and I propose that we are
using that same model when we're trying
to explain the cognitive continuum we're
using the current scientific method of
trying to afford a synoptic integration
for example between these discourses
that have to do with the phenomenology
and training and between the discourses
that have to do with the functionality
it makes
right so something that I was thinking
about just yesterday as I was working on
some of the writing is that it seems
that one thing we might actually be
doing is pulling another set of
disciplines into this synoptic
integration process and that would be
the more spiritual and philosophically
oriented traditions which are much more
pragmatically oriented yes
and I think I mean well philosophy
itself has a huge and important role
within cognitive science precisely
because one of the things that
philosophy has been very good at is
exactly this process of trying to get
different domains of discourse and human
endeavor and human existence to talk to
each other reliably you can even see
this in ancient philosophy the ancient
philosophers are trying to say well you
know how does our ethics and our
knowledge and our relationship to the
gods and how do we get these to all talk
to each other so there's some sort of
coherent integrated life that is livable
for us hmm stoicism in particular is a
good example of that yes Platonism as
well
yes very much oriented on living the
good life yes very much and if we have a
discipline of studying the mind then
like why would we also not want to study
the good life as well I think I think a
good analogy in the ancient world in
fact for modern cognitive science is
ancient philosophy because ancient
philosophy isn't as limited in its scope
and self-identification as modern
academic philosophy I believe in modern
academic philosophy I'm not criticizing
you and you do too obviously but what I
mean is in ancient philosophy you you
had something much more like the
integration of what you might call
modern conceptual analysis and
theorization with you know what hadou
calls Spiritual Exercises so you've got
psychology and sort of philosophy and
the best science of the time and the
best training practices the best
pedagogy how to educate people how to
how to inspire them to aspire you're
doing much much more and I think that's
a little bit closer analogy from
cognitive sciences in fact what we're
kind of doing I think what you're
suggesting is we're taking cognitive
science and we're trying to bring in
that that missing piece of inspiring
people to aspiration and to afford them
actually training that you see present
in ancient philosophy
I would definitely concur with that
definitely there is a lot of benefit to
bringing back this sort of integrative
approach and on the
the integrative approach I think that's
a really good jumping point to talk
about the role of mystical experiences
and also how various traditions have
gone about the process of particular
izing those mystical experiences to fit
the context of their time there was a
conversation that you had recently which
you posted on your channel about this
sort of religion that's not a religion
yes one of the ideas that really stood
out to me about that video was the idea
of the trade-off between compression and
particular ization
yet in the process of taking a more sort
of mystical experience all engaged
approach to a spiritual tradition or
philosophy so one thing to go back to
that discussion about perennialism
versus eclecticism one thing that's
really important to notice is that the
various spiritual traditions which are
oriented towards something like
enlightenment and admittedly they use
different terminology format so just by
using enlightenment we're already
applying an integrative norm by saying
well you know let's explain these things
by collecting the invariance and that's
our definition but it's also important
to note which particular traditions are
good for which things right so if you
look at Christianity and Buddhism which
we're going to be contrasting there are
certain trends of interpretation in
those which are exactly the opposite
right so Buddha comes from a rich family
and he decides to leave that to live in
a sea decline he has first off the
choice to do that and he has material
comfort
whereas Christ as somebody who's coming
from a relatively poor family in a
war-torn City and he doesn't really have
a lot going for him but it's by God's
grace that he is you know the Christ to
the Messiah and it's actually it flies
in the face of the expectations of the
people at the time because they're
looking for a son of David became the
glorious one who will you know be
elevated to the highest position in
society etc so that's one thing that
really throws people off in the early
Christian age they think well you know
this like poor worker type couldn't
possibly be madness how can that be the
son of David who we've been expecting
and there's a great book which I've seen
you referenced
few times called the religion of the
future by Roberto Unger he does an
excellent job of articulating the
various different attitudes that can be
taken to these sort of be more universal
spiritual phenomena you know there is
something like a perennialism going on
because we all have the same
neurocognitive constraints as a result
we all have access to similar
experiences the experience and divine
union is one of those it's something
that just as a result in the particular
kind of nervous system we've been
endowed with most if not everybody can
achieve now while that is the case you
know there is a perennial state of mind
that people have access to based on me
particularity is a context people have
to solve different problems right so the
problem that boot is that the boot is
trying to solve are a little bit
different just because of the society in
which she lives and so the approach that
becomes dominant there is what buglar
refers to as overcoming the world yes he
lived in a very rigid hierarchical
society where social movement isn't
really very possible so he sets aside a
place outside of society to which people
go and we work on just overcoming
attachment overcoming desire and just
being simply happy here and now the
Christian view on the other hand very
very different it's something that many
thinkers have argued has informed the
products of modern liberalism and
romanticism etc it's hard to divorce
those from the religious history and
within the Christian view there's much
more of an imperative on transforming
the world right so Buddhism is very much
transform the self
whereas in Christianity you have to
participate in a community and actively
transform your relationships and the
society such that it is more worthy of
God when he comes through the final
judgement and so one thing that's going
to become apparent in the process of
this book is that we're gonna be taking
lessons from different traditions based
on which ones have the best language to
explain and promote engagement with a
particular issue Buddhism for example
and parasitic processing go very well
together yes you know that's you had a
whole episode on that denier awakened
the meeting crisis series but again for
Christianity there's other problems
which
tradition is a little bit better suited
to responsive I think that's excellent
so one way of thinking about that and
that's to do with sort of broader scope
of my work you've heard me use this
analogy before is evolution by natural
selection and the idea is there are
perennial aspects as you said because
across all environments creatures have
to adapt they have to survive that to
reproduce and so what Darwin does is he
comes up with the sort of universal
principles by which that process occurs
but that doesn't mean that all of the
particular adaptations are homogeneous
in fact what it predicts is exactly the
opposite in this context right this
niche adaptivity we'll look this way
well having this morphology in this
right so it's neither it's neither a
kind of perennialism that every every
every every creature because they're
adaptive is altima the same but neither
is it a kind of relativism or
eclecticism it's no no no the very fact
that they're so well suited to these
varying environments can be given a
comprehensive integrated explanation and
that's exactly I think what we're trying
to do here we're trying to show that
synaptic integration tries to get both
of those it tries to say there are
aspects that we can explain that are
universal in the processing but because
of the nature of our explanation that
will predict that we should see that
right the various instantiations are
going to be fitted to their historical
cultural context right Clayton is I
think it's us a really good language for
sort of grappling with this problem
there is this sort of universal simple
one which everyone can happen to contact
with but its nature is that it is
absolutely simple absolutely good and
simplicity is just fundamentally opposed
to the kind of world that we live in
it's like the opposite almost we live in
the world of maximal complexity thus
simply residing in the unit of bliss of
that simplistic unit of frame of mind
doesn't really allow you the license to
the
and collapse all particularity of
complexity into that that's not where we
live right now I live in the world of
complexity in fact I think it's like
what you see in evolution where you get
you know variation and then selection on
it or what you see in machine learning
you get variation and then you get
compression and then but you cycle you
cycle and that's part of what we're
arguing to right that you shouldn't you
should what you should see is that this
state as you say of unity isn't to be
equated with the cultivation of wisdom
it's actually the ability to cycle and
open just enhance your overall activity
that's what that is how these states can
actually contribute to enlightenment and
and and that goes towards our point that
we are not just taking sort of the
traditional meanings of enlightenment
where we're doing we're treating them
with respect but we're not just taking
them again because of the the
phenomenological language of training
we're actually giving sort of an
operational definition of enlightenment
in terms of its ability right - we're
defining it in terms of these states
that afford the ability for human beings
to comprehensively address perennial
problems printed problems of self
deceptive self-destructive behavior
getting existentially confused in their
modes all this sort so we are doing
another cognitive science thing we're
sort of or we're reverse engineering
enlightenment in terms of well what
problems should it solve
rather than trying to get in what seems
to have been an interminable and
irresolvable debate about from the
phenomenology what enlightenment is it's
sort of like well this is what we need
enlightenment to do because given the
nature of the machinery the adaptive
machinery these are the kinds of
perennial problems it's facing and so
enlightenment should significantly
reliably and systematically be able to
address those and of course there's
going to be a component of that that we
can sort of specify in universal terms
and then we're going to predict whether
it would predict that there's gonna be
ways in which again that adaptivity
is going to be specified I think it's
really important to emphasize that point
you made that simply the occurrence of a
mystical experience
on its own not enough to guarantee
enlightenment the trade-off between the
compression and the particular ization
is what's really going to enable you to
apply the potential of the unit of
experience which is why I've focused a
lot in my own writing in my own research
on the visionary experience because the
visionary experience is one where in
particular ation particular ization is
ongoing yes so you're getting
imaginative metaphors that you can
grapple with and maybe those are those
metaphors are sort of a networking of
various things that have happened in
your life there's okay I have to give
this example because it's one of my
favorite examples but the capacity for
imaginative insight as a result of
mental imagery based experience it's so
profound and so powerful you barely even
have to try to make it happen especially
if you are under the influence of
psychedelic compounds such as LSD
psilocybin and these things that allow
your brain to really snap into new forms
of order there is a paper that was
published in 2017 I think it was and the
authors were merely exploring whether or
not the imagery in the LSD experience
was similar to the imagery that comes up
in dreams so they're trying to look at a
measure which is called cognitive
bizarreness it's like an okay measure
but very subjective of course you have
to have a number of writers decide if
it's bizarre or not so one of the people
who are in this study they have no
mental health conditions they're you
know just average as normal as you could
possibly get because we're just looking
at this very basic functional thing and
they ask very minimal questions so
they'll have it the researcher in the
room and he'll just be like oh what do
you see what next
etc and so one of the participants has
the following experience he says okay so
I'm in a field and I see there's a beach
over there and it's a pirate ship I
gotta go hang out in the pirate ship all
right now I'm in the basement of this
pirate ship and there is a treasure
chest I can open this treasure chest and
it's empty and oh my god I've been
focusing too much of my time on work and
neglecting my relationships I really
need to go like tell my wife that I love
her it's so funny like no intention at
all but already his imagination is just
Italy structured in such a way that
there are meaningful insights lurking
just beneath the surface of this imagery
yeah I think that's amazing I think I
mean if you think about it that that
movement between compression and
particular ization well this is part of
what we argue it has a lot to do with
the processes you need and in solving an
inside problem not to break up in an
appropriate frame if to expand back out
but then you have to come back in and
you can even see that be playing out and
ships between the hemisphere between you
know the left hemisphere which tends to
emphasize details step-by-step program
progress the right hemisphere that tends
to emphasize the squished all trying to
gather it all together and what insight
is is not to be in one place or the
other but to have this optimal kind of
movement between them but also you know
if we want to ask well why exactly does
the state of mystical insight feel as
though it's so infused with truth that
our normal everyday experience isn't
well the right temporal lobe is also
something that processes comprehension
right there is hemispheric
lateralization in much of your
processing especially when it comes to
things like language and sense making
and your left hemisphere is more
specialized in the production of
language which whereas the right is more
specialized in the comprehension of
language so you're basically having like
a tiny seizure in the area of your brain
that processes comprehension so of
course you're gonna feel Oh
comprehension just immersing everything
because that's where the source of the
moment is coming from yeah and it's also
that that because it tends to move to
that more Gestalt which overall
integration that's also paired up with a
sense of not just comprehension but
importance because the Gestalt things
were usually these are areas where we're
dealing with very messy ill-defined
problems often that have a kind of
urgency to them so when so the left
hemisphere is very good at handling
there's familiar well-defined problems
the right hemisphere is much better for
unfamiliar ill-defined things and
typically unfamiliar they'll defined
things are either very threatening or
very wonderful and therefore they carry
with them you sort of they portend
since right and important so it's not
only that you're getting sort of this
enhanced sense of intelligibility you're
getting an enhanced sense of oh this is
really important but as we've said like
if you get caught up with the imagery
and thinking it's giving you a literal
account you can get my stuff but if you
realize oh but that sense of importance
is actually if it's true of you're
solving problems then something really
significant in terms of training you're
processing is going on so for example we
following earlier work that I've done we
argue that you know what you can do is
you can trim you can chain a bunch of
insights together into getting an
insight cascade where one insight sort
of you know provides and provokes
another one and so on and you can see
people doing this when they're playing
jazz right or when they're rock climbing
or when you're sparring and the thing
and that's when you primarily get into a
flow state by doing that kind of thing
now the thing about the flow state is
you know chicks have Mahad calls it
optimal experiences it's a question
related to our ideas of optimal gripping
of reality right now because it's
optimal in two ways both people regard
it is a really great experience not
pleasurable but more this sense of
discovery and importance and at one mid
with reality but also this is where well
think of the jazz musician or the
athlete in the zone or the martial
artist or the rock climbing I mean
athletes try to get into the flow state
precisely because it's also optimal
performance and that's ultimately what
we're trying to get point people towards
thinking about this more in terms of
optimal performance rather than you know
the the semantic veracity of the
propositions so the nature enlightenment
one thing that we're arguing is that
well it's not let me a property we have
in the historical discourse claims
bottom line to people but it doesn't
seem that enlightenment is best
described as a property that a person
can obtain and if you look at for
example the christian the orthodox
christian writer from the 4th century
gregory eveness is it was what I've
heard ok so he talks about epic TASIS
that's correct right so that was great I
I'm glad that you threw that my
direction so epic Isis is described as
so it translates into like a straining
towards and it's this never-ending
process
of trying to keep pace with this
transcendent ideal yeah it's the idea
that God is the inexhaustible nosov God
is is perpetually affording the self
transcendence that human beings fine
gives them such a tremendous sense of
connectedness to what's most real so
it's different from more typical
mythology in which what you're what
you're trying to do for example perhaps
in a Christian life is to get to a state
of sort of blessed rest a sort of a
final a final place a final position of
final status and epic thesis was this
much this interesting idea that what's
happening is instead no no our
relationship to the sacred isn't to try
and finalize any kind of grasp of it and
think about again but the analogy with
evolution there is no final fitted 'no
sporran isms they constantly have to be
evolving across generations or they will
fall out of sync with reality and so
again the epic thesis is is is that idea
and this has even picked up by people
like Schlegel when he talks about the
finite constantly longing for the
infinite that well so this that this
understanding and I like this which is
why I recommended it to you because this
notion of the sacredness of these
experience does not give you this idea
of well here's the final content that I
have to hold on to it's rather no this
is an ongoing performance of self
transcendence and what I have to do is
find out how to keep the music flowing
I'm glad to use the music metaphor as a
musician very accessible I've been
really bringing a lot of my experience
playing music into looking at how to
work with the flow state in particular
in service of this idea of sort of
keeping pace with the transcendent I
metaphor that I realize might be pretty
good for this I hope that as science
progresses it doesn't make this metaphor
irrelevant but the ideal of the
transcendent which enlightenment is
oriented towards something like a black
hole you can't really fully see it it's
something that is a little bit beyond
our capacity to comprehend but it has an
immense pole once you're in its horizon
yeah
so they can like mint - something like
that it's an ideal to aspire towards and
once we do end up bringing our state of
being our existential mode into pace
with the event horizon of the ideal it
will have more and more of a pull more
and more of a feel and actually there's
a great Buddhist symbol which is used
it's showing up in tattoos a lot because
it's been used a lot in these sort of
sacred tattoo tradition which is famous
for from Thailand but the symbol is it's
like a swirl which starts out with like
a lot of layers and then eventually it
breaks out of the swirl becomes a zag a
zigzag line and then a straight line
upwards and that's supposed to describe
the process of enlightenment which is
exactly
I think constant but this idea we're
getting out yes it's really complicated
you're running in circles a lot but once
you get it it becomes easier and easier
to keep pace of it well I like the zig
zagging too because the zig zagging is a
better it sort of picks up from the
compression particularization
all right moving between until
eventually you you you arc into some
optimal optimal flow state perhaps I'll
have to include one thing I'm trying to
do which i think is important to mention
as well is to add a lot of art into this
I think that's extremely relevant and I
think that's I mean that's that's kind
of a godsend for our partnership because
you're bringing that artistic ability in
that I don't possess and what you've
probably seen in some of the videos and
discussions I've had with people I keep
arguing that that if we're going to
respond to things like the meaning
crisis it can't just be even it's not
sufficient just to use theory or even to
do ecologies of sort of practice we need
what Corbin called the imaginal we need
the artistic expression to link those
two domains together Justin optically
integrate them so they can insightfully
inform and transform each other to your
credit you can draw a meme 9da problem
but yeah so out of more serious notes
the inclusion of art is going to be
something that I hope elevates people's
experience of the book as well so I'm
commissioning a number of artists to
draw some pieces that are you know
relevant to whichever perspectives we're
trying to elucidate linguistically
because if we're gonna be taking
seriously the ideas that we're giving
you know there's a lot of different ways
of knowing and the proposition is only
one of them yeah
everybody can access proposition equally
it's in order to make this knowledge
accessible I think it's really important
to provide also a more perspective
participatory image oriented
articulation of the ideas as well
I agree with that totally and like I
said I think it's a godsend that you're
bringing that to the book thank you I'm
having a lot of fun well that's good fun
helps definitely helps the aspirational
aspect so perhaps maybe we should go
back now and talk a little bit about the
campaign and what you want to say about
it what you want to explain about it
sure so I'm still sort of finalizing
preparing but the campaign should be
launching actually by the time this
video is that will already be larger so
that's not really relevant to mention
what is relevant to mention is that the
link will be in the description of this
video so it'll be easy to find you'll be
able to find an elaboration of all of
the costs that are associated with this
right we have to pay these artists to
draw these pieces we also have to pay
for the cost of actually designing the
layout and the cover and all said I want
Daniel to have an income he's putting in
lots of time and effort on this people
should know though that I'm not taking
any income from this campaign I want to
I wanted to go part of what you many of
you know as I'd like to try and afford
other people's careers and to get them
going and so Daniel is putting a
tremendous it's this is work really work
of love for him I into this book and so
part of the money will go towards
supporting his labour and the other
things that he's addressing yeah
definitely don't make it more possible
for me to get this done on time
yes we're trying to finish by April 30th
yes we are and I'm gonna need to
basically treat this like a full-time
job if we're gonna make it happen inside
that's right that's right
yeah so just to briefly touch on some of
the perks there's gonna be a unique
piece of content from you a paper that
you've written you know self-published
that so if you want access to some more
John content you will have the option to
participate in that as well there's also
an option to participate in the editing
process so you can sign up for what's
called beta reader privileges if you
want really access to some of it and
also to
gives feedback on what makes sense what
doesn't what you like what you don't
like that'll really help us to make the
book accessible to a wide audience while
also helping us to gather the funds that
we need to actually execute this and
there's a lot else you can go check that
out on your own if you'd like I don't
think there's too much else aside from
that you mention unless you have any
final thoughts no just like I said I
think I'm very excited for this project
going forward I think this book is an
excellent compliment and that's how it
is intended to be used to their series
awakening from the mating crisis so
Daniel thank you very very much for your
time thank you
[Music]
you